[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Three]
[第三集]
I invited you here today
我今天请你们来
because I want to repair my image in your minds.
是想修补我在二位心中的形象
This is the batch that just came out.
这是刚刚出炉的批作
Please enjoy.
请二位笑纳
That's wonderful!
可真是太好了啊
Wait, wait, wait!
等等等等等等
It's not finished, it's not finished!
没完呢啊没完呢
I can't write this for nothing.
我这字啊它不能白写
It has to be commissioned.
它要收润笔的
Brother Zhong Fu.
仲甫兄啊
Your writing is in a class of its own.
你的字是自成一体
It's hard to find a good writer.
笔力雄健千金难求
As long as the gentleman is willing to write for us,
只要先生愿意给我们写
it's not a problem.
这个自然不在话下
Okay, then I won't charge more.
好那我也不多收
Two hundred silver dollars per print.
每幅字两百大洋
Don't worry, no problem!
放心 没问题
Good!
好
Don't!
别
Don't rush!
别着急
We're not done yet.
还没说完呢
I'd like to write more than one.
我呀 要写就不止写一幅
One per month.
每月一幅
What do you think?
二位意下如何
Yes, monthly.
对 每月
No, it's a bit strange, isn't it?
不是 这有点奇怪吧
Aiyo...
哎哟
Aiyo... yoyoyo...
哎哟 哟哟哟
This is rare.
真是难得
One per month!
每月一幅
I've been with Zhongfu for so many years
我跟仲甫老弟这么多年
that I don't even have one of his calligraphies in my hand.
手上连他一幅字都没有
Naturally.
那是
What about you?
怎么样你们收不收
I'll take it if you won't.
不收我收了
Brother Mengzou, Brother Zhong Fu.
孟邹兄 仲甫兄
You seem to have ulterior motives.
你们这是醉翁之意不在酒啊
Right!
是啊
One per month, 200 per print.
每月一幅 每幅二百
We'll take it!
我们收了
Take it!
收了
Good, Brother Menzou, write up the contract.
好 孟邹兄 拟合同
Brother Mengzou, what you just said,
孟邹兄啊 你刚才那个
Aiyo... aiyo...
哎哟 哎哟
Aiyo... yoyoyo...
哎哟 哟哟哟
It's so faked!
太假了
Brother.
哥
[Chen Qiaonian, second son of Chen Duxiu]
[陈乔年 陈独秀次子]
Forget Henian,
鹤年也就算了
but Zimei is a little girl,
但子美她是个小姑娘
how can she like this?
她能喜欢这玩意儿吗
[Chen Yannian, eldest son of Chen Duxiu]
[陈延年 陈独秀长子]
I also want to buy her a doll.
我还想给她买洋娃娃呢
But where is the money?
可哪儿有钱啊
Cut quickly!
快劈吧
It's a hot day!
这大热天的
What are you two doing in the house?
你们俩在屋鼓坞什么呢
Is it hot?
热不热呀
Come and eat watermelon. Eat watermelon.
来吃西瓜 吃西瓜
Come on, it's sweet. Come on, come on.
来 可甜了 来来来
Thank you.
谢谢您
Thank you Uncle Wang.
谢谢汪伯伯
Let me tell you both.
我跟你们俩说啊
In a moment, your father
一会儿你父亲
will be talking to some important guests.
要和几位重要的客人谈大事
[Wang Mengzou, Manager of Yadong Library]
[汪孟邹 亚东图书馆经理]
You have to think about the bigger picture.
你们得顾全大局啊
Not like last time,
不能像上次
with frogs, snakes
弄些什么什么青蛙啊蛇呀
mites and other messy things.
娱臭虫什么乱七八糟的么螨子
Do that again, I won't allow you in.
再那样做 我不答应啊
What's this?
这是什么
It's for Zimei.
给 给子美的
Did you hear what I just told you?
我刚才跟你说的听清楚了吗
Don't worry, I know what's important.
您放心 我知道轻重
My problem with him
我跟他的过节
was made clear that day.
那天就已经讲清楚了
He will not be embarrassed anymore.
不会再难为他
That's good!
这就对了嘛
Your father was a great man.
你父亲是干大事的人
We can't let him get distracted.
我们可不能让他分心
Zhong Fu!
仲甫
Brother Xing Yan, I'm glad you're back!
行严兄 可把你盼回来了
Missed you so much!
想死你了
Go, go, go!
快快快
General Zou.
邹将军
Brother Xing Yan, how are you?
行严兄 你好啊
Here I come.
来了 我
That's really for Zimei?
那真是给子美的
And for Henian.
还有给鹤年的
Right, right, right.
行行行
You two stay inside and don't go out!
你们俩在屋里别出去了啊
Eat your watermelon.
吃你们的西瓜
Alright.
好
Mr. Xing Yan!
行严先生
Brother Mengzou!
孟邹兄
Welcome, welcome, welcome!
欢迎欢迎欢迎啊
Come on, come on, come on, have a seat.
来来来 快请坐快请坐
Sit, sit, sit.
坐坐坐
Have a seat.
快坐
Meeting Mr. Zhongshan and General Huang Xing
为了见中山先生和黄兴将军
delayed a few more days on the road.
路上多耽搁了几天
How's it going? What's the situation in Shanghai?
怎么样 上海的形势如何
The anti-Yuan movement has taken root in people's hearts,
反袁思想已经深入人心了
it is unstoppable.
势不可挡
It's just that the Yuan forces' repressive tactics
只是袁党的镇压手段
are getting more and more brutal.
也越来越凶残了
Yes, there were many deaths everywhere.
是 各地都死了好多人
But I have no doubt
不过我坚信
[Chen Duxiu, styled Zhong Fu, chief editor of "Youth Magazine"]
[陈独秀 字 仲甫 《青年杂志》主编]
that their actions will not be in vain.
他们的栖性是不会白费的
By the way, Zhong Fu,
话说回来啊 仲甫
[Zhang Tuzhao, styled Xing Yan, organizer of "The Tiger" magazine]
[章土钊 字 行严 《甲寅》杂志刨办人]
you're always so efficient!
你这办事效率历来地高啊
[Zou Yongcheng, styled Qi Zhi]
[邹永城 字 器之]
So many comrades gathered at once.
一下子就聚集了这么多同志
It's not that I'm efficient,
不是我办事效率高
it's that we've all been so desperate for so long
是大家都急眼了
that we're going crazy.
整这么长时间都快疯了
It's a great opportunity to be active!
这总算有机会能不积极吗
Right, right.
是啊 是啊
Let's meet then!
那咱们开会啊
Let me pass on Mr. Zhongshan's instructions
让我传达一下中山先生的指示
Alright.
好
The situation is now in our favour.
现在的形势对我们来说是有利的
The world powers are at war in Europe
世界上列强在欧洲打仗
and can't be bothered with our China.
顾不上我们中国
At home,
而在国内
Yuan Shikai is trying to claim the throne
袁世凯为了顺利称帝
by increasing suppression of anti-Yuan activists.
加大了对反袁人士的镇压力度
But such a high-handed policy
可如此高压政策
has instead given us
反而让我们获得了
a lot of public support.
大量群众的支持
Thus Mr. Zhongshan and General Huang Xing
由此中山先生和黄兴将军
asked us to take active action
要求我们积极行动起来
to protect our country,
林马厉兵
as soon as the time is right,
旦时机成熟立刻举兵护国
to overthrow Yuan Shikai's reactionary rule
推翻袁世凯的反动统治
to and create a new republic.
再造一个薪新的共和
I, at the behest of Mr. Zhong Fu,
我在仲甫先生的授意下
ran the magazine in my hometown.
以回乡办杂志为名啊
I organized a team
组织了一支队伍
which has now grown to over two thousand members.
现在已经发展到子两千多人
Whenever there is an incident in Yunnan,
只要云南一起事
we in Hunan will be the first to respond
我湘人首先响应
and turn the world upside down.
搅他一个天翻地覆
Nice work!
干得漂亮
Why do I get the impression
我怎么觉得
that Zhong Fu is in charge of the army?
是仲甫在坐镇中军呢
It's only been three days, you seem different than before.
真的是士别三日当刮目相看
I've heard you've got something big.
听说你有大手笔
Tell us about it.
给我们说一说吧
I can't continue fighting and quarrelling forever.
我呀这个打架吵架的事做不了
I'm still doing my old job, writing.
我还是干我的老本行 写字
For the past two months, I and Baisha have been staying at home
这两个月我跟易白沙足不出户
running a magazine called "Youth Magazine".
办了一本杂志叫《青年杂志》
The goal was to promote a new culture,
本意是鼓吹新文化宣传新思想
to create a new generation of young people
造就新青年
with the most advanced ideas
就是想用世界上
and theories in the world,
最先进的思想理论
in order to replace the one that has ruled China for thousands of years:
来替代统治了中国几千年的
the Three Principles of Confucianism.
孔教三纲
Under the banner of science and democracy,
用科学与民主的旗帜
a new generation of youth will be reinvented.
重塑一代新青年
This is a sketch of the inaugural issue.
这是创刊号的草样
Gentlemen, share your thoughts.
各位先生指教
Brother Zhong Fu,
仲甫兄
why is there a foreigner on this cover?
这封面上怎么是个外国人
Who is this?
这谁呀
Carnegie!
卡内基呀
The steel king and philanthropist.
钢铁大王兼慈善家
He is Scottish.
他是苏格兰人
At the age of eleven, he moved to America
十一岁迫于生计移居美国
and worked in a textile factory to make ends meet.
为了糊口在纺织厂打过工
Firing boilers,
烧过锅炉
working as a courrier...
做过快递员
Then, through his own ingenuity and hard work,
后来靠着自身的聪明和努力
established his own company
建立了自己的公司
alongside Rockefeller and Morgan
创建了与洛克菲勒和摩根
creating a steel empire...
并立的钢铁帝国
It became one of the three giants of the American economy.
成了美国经济三大巨头之一
The reason I put Carnegie
我之所以把卡内基
as the cover of our inaugural issue
作为我们创刊号的封面人物
is that we want to tell
就是想告诉那些
the children of China who are still suffering
还在吃苦受罪的中国孩子们
that the way of the world is left to the people of this world
天下的路是留给天下的人走的
and where there is a will, there is a way.
有志者事竟成
Zhong Fu, you promote new cultures and new ideas.
仲甫 你宣传新文化新思想
I'm all for it.
我双手赞成
But if you reject Confucianism in its entirety,
可若是你全盘否定孔子儒学
I cannot accept.
我不赞成
Brother Xing Yan, not all of it.
行严兄 不是全盘
Listen to me carefully
你听我慢慢地
and in detail.
细细地跟你说好吧
Let's go.
来
[Aurora University auditorium, Shanghai]
[上海震旦学院礼堂]
Some people say that you, Chen Duxiu, started a magazine
有人说 你陈独秀创办杂志
to awaken the nation's political
是为了唤醒国人政治的
and ethical consciousness.
和伦理的觉悟
So what is this awakening?
那么这个觉悟究竞是什么
As everyone knows,
大家知道
after Lin Zexu banned opium,
道光年林则徐禁了鸦片
the British invaded China.
英国人就打进了中国
With their strong ships and powerful guns,
人家船坚炮利
we were defeated.
我们一败涂地
So some people suggested
于是有人就提出
that we should learn from the barbarians to control them.
要师夷长技以制夷
This is the first awakening.
这是第一道觉悟
Knowing that you are not as good as others
知道自己技不如人
and the need to learn from them.
要向人家学习
Later on, some people also further realized
后来 有人也进一步认识到
that we are not only inferior in skills
我们不光技不如人
but also in country.
最重费的是国不如人
The foreigners had a more advanced system than we did,
洋人有比我们先进的制度
so they came up with the Hundred Days' Reform and the New Deal of the late Qing Dynasty.
于是就有了成成变法 晚清新政
Until the Xinhai Revolution overthrew the imperial system
直至辛玄革命推翻帝制
and established a republic.
建立了共和
This is the second awakening.
这是第二道觉悟
But what about the establishment of the Republic?
可是建立了民国又怎么样呢
The foreigners are still bullying us.
洋人照样欺负我们
The people still don't have enough to eat.
老百姓照样吃不饱饭
Here's why.
这是为什么
It's not just that we're not as good as others,
这就不光是我们技不如人
with a system not as good as theirs.
制度不如人
The most fundamental thing
最根本的
is our ideological and moral philosophy.
是我们思想 道德 理念
which is less advanced than others.
不如人家先进
That's why I say that all enlightenment
所以我说 所有觉悟归根结底
is ultimately the enlightenment of the mind
就是思想的觉悟
and the awareness of moral philosophy.
道德理念的觉悟
This is the final awakening.
这最后的觉悟
In the end, it's all about human awareness.
说到底 人的觉悟
This final awakening is to change our minds
这最后的觉悟就是要换脑子
to find the most advanced ideas in the world
要找到世界上最先进的思想
to arm our people
来武装我们的人民
to shape a new generation of youth
来塑造新一代青年
to create a new nation!
来创造一个崭新的国家
Yes! Yes! Yes!
好 好 好
For the new youth in contemporary China,
当代中国的新青年
I think there should be six criteria.
我以为应该有六个标准
First, one must be independent, not servile.
一 自主的 而非奴隶的
Second, one must be progressive, not conservative.
二 进步的 而非保守的
Third, one must be aggressive, not reclusive.
三 进取的 而非退隐的
Fourth, one must be international, not isolated.
四 世界的 而非锁国的
Fifth, one must be practical, not illusory.
五 实利的 而非虚文的
Sixth, one must be scientific, not imaginary.
第六 科学的 而非想象的
The six criteria are,
六条标准
in a nutshell, that science and democracy
总的来说 就是科学与民主
should create a new generation of young people,
要造就一代新青年
and the only way to do this is to use both science and democracy.
唯有用科学和民主并重
Science and democracy are the criteria
科学与民主就是检验
by which politics, law, ethics, academia,
政治 法律 伦理 学术
social customs
以及社会风俗
and the daily lives of people
和人们日常生活
are judged.
一言一行的准绳
Anything that is contrary to science and democracy,
凡是违反科学与民主的
even if it is the legacy of our ancestors,
哪怕是祖宗之遗留
the teachings of our sages
圣贤之垂教
and the veneration of society
社会之崇尚
is not worth promoting.
皆不值得提倡
Yes! Yes! Yes!
好 好 好
Science and democracy are the sunrise,
科学和民主是朝阳
but today
而现如今
the country is a mouldy, rotten
国家却是一个被捂得严严实实的
sore and bleeding
发着霉 烂着疮
old house that is covered up tightly.
流着胺的老房子
How about letting the sun of science and democracy
怎么样才能让科学和民主的阳光
shine on the house?
照亮房子呢
In the past we used the simplest method,
过去我们用最简单的方法
knocking down old houses.
推倒老房子
But you knocked down the house!
可是你推倒了这房子
The mould, the sores, the glue are still hidden inside.
那霉 那疮 那胶还依然藏在里面
What grows is still rotten and dirty.
长出来的还依然是腐朽的脏东西
So, China must be strong.
所以 中国要强大
Not only do we need to knock down the house,
我们不仅要推掉那所房子
but more importantly,
更重要的是
we need to dig out the roots of its decay
我们要挖掉其腐朽的根源
to bring about a profound intellectual revolution
来一场深刻的思想革命
using the ideas of science and democracy
用科学与民主的理念
to arm our youth.
来武装我们的青年
How to arm them?
怎么武装
Everyone is looking for answers.
大家都在探索
My opinion is that
我的意见是
we should start with the daily life
先让我们从入心入脑的
that is in our hearts and minds,
日常生活做起
starting with our speech and writing.
先从我们说话写字做起
Promoting the vernacular,
提倡白话文
to speak in words that everyone can understand
说大家都能听懂的话
and write words that everyone can read.
写大家都能看明白的文字
We need to use the power of new literature
我们要用新文学的力量
to enlighten the public mind.
来启蒙大众的思想
Yes!
好
Well spoken!
讲得好
September 15, 1915
一九一五年九月十五日
Chen Duxiu founds the "Youth Magazine" in Shanghai.
陈独秀在上海创办《青年杂志》
The New Culture movement for the enlightenment of modern Chinese thought
现代中国思想启蒙的新文化运动
came into being.
应运而生
[Waseda University domitory, Japan]
[日本早稻田大学宿舍]
I say this Chen Duxiu
我说这个陈独秀啊
is really not a master of empty words.
还真不是一个说空话的主
Just a few months after returning to China,
刚回国几个月
he has done such an amazing thing.
就办了这么一个惊天动地的事来
It may be late autumn
现在虽然是深秋
but did you know?
但是你知道吗
When I took from him this "Youth Magazine",
我从他这本《青年杂志》上
I smelt a whiff of spring.
闻到了一股春天的味道
[Li Dazhao, styled Shou Chang, student at Waseda University]
[李大钊 字 守常 日本早稻田大学学生]
Chen Duxiu is not a simple man.
陈独秀 不简单哪
It's finally happening
终于出手了
[Gao Yihan, student at Waseda University]
[高一涵 日本早稻田大学学生]
and it's a bombshell!
而且一出手就是个惊天大炸雷
I now finally understand
我现在算是终于明白
what he meant by this self-consciousness.
他这个自觉心是什么意思了
Brother Shou Chang,
守常兄
Two months ago you were clamouring
两个月前你还整天嚷嚷着
to criticise Chen Duxiu for his pessimistic and self-conscious approach to the world.
要批评陈独秀悲观庆世的自觉心
In the blink of an eye,
这一转眼 怎么
how did you become his best friend?
你就成了他的死党了
Right?
对不对
It's been two months on the island, and a thousand years in the Middle Kingdom.
岛上刚两月 中原已千年啊
I think at first, he said you couldn't take love of country
想当初 他说不能把爱国
and love of that corrupt government,
和爱那个腐朽政府
comparing them against each other.
相提并论的时候
How many people are complaining?
那多少人骂声一片
But what about now?
可是现在呢
Overthrowing Yuan has become the consensus of the whole country.
倒袁已经成为了全中国的共识
At this point
在这一点上
you have to admit
你不得不承认
that Chen Duxiu had a great vision.
陈独秀还是眼光独到的
Too much.
太多
Is that enough?
够了吗
You're killing me.
你购死我
Yihan.
一涵
Awakening the minds of the people
唤醒民众的思想觉悟
is also something I have always wanted to do to
也是我一直想做的事
I can't read this book anymore.
这个书我念不下去了
This is a letter from him to me.
这是他给我的来信
I hope that our Chinese Students Association
希望咱们中国问题研究会
will contribute to the "Youth Magazine" in large numbers.
踊跃给《青年杂志》投稿
[Changsha, Hunan Province]
[湖南长沙]
Out of the way!
让开
Everyone, out of the way!
把路口让开
Out of the way! Out of the way!
让开 让开
[Mao Zedong, styled Run Zhi, student at Hunan Provincial First Normal School]
[毛泽东 字 润之 湖南省立第一师范学校学生]
Selling a child!
卖孩子啦
A well-behaved child!
多乖巧的孩子
Sir, would you like a take a look?
先生要不要看看
"Friends wanted:"
征友启事
"From '28 Strokes Student'"
二十八画生者
"Commoner student from Changsha"
长沙布衣学子也
"who can endure hardships and toil"
但有能耐限苦劳顿
"to serve the nation with unstinting selflessness."
不惜己身而为国家者
"Is in search of:"
修远求索
"Fellow travellers"
上下而欲觅同道者
"From far and wide."
皆吾之所求也
"Which is to say, seeking friends"
故日 愿樱鸣以求友
"Like a bird screaming for assistance."
敢步将伯之呼
How novel!
新鲜哪
Even the classifieds can be used to make friends.
这征友也贴告示
Are we helping this '28 Strokes Student'
咱们是为这个二十八画生
find a wife?
招亲娶媳妇吗
Mr. Yu Heng.
玉衡先生
Foreign persimmons
洋柿子
Here, try it.
来 尝尝
You too.
你也来一个
You've misunderstood
这位同学
this classmate.
你误会了
He is
他呀
looking for a friend
是想找一个
with the same common purpose of serving the country.
能够同心协力报效国家的净友
How grand.
气势不小
You all
你们这里
seem to be making a pact of brotherhood.
倒有点桃园结义的意思啊
Who is this '28 Strokes Student'?
这二十八画生是哪一位
Ma, '28 Strokes Student'
妈 二十八画生
is Mao Zedong.
是毛泽东
You know, Runzhi.
润之啊
That kid is something!
这子厉害喽
[Li Lisan, student at Hunan Provincial First Normal School]
打扰一下
Excuse me,
请问
[Xiao Zisheng, student at Hunan Provincial First Normal School]
你们谁是二十八画生啊
Hello, hello.
你好你好
I am here to apply for the meeting of friends.
我是来应征会友的
My name is Cai Hesen.
我叫蔡和森
How do you do?
你好你好
This is Xiao Zisheng.
这位是萧子升
My hands are covered with ink.
我这手上都是油墨
Chen Chang.
陈昌
Hello.
你好
This one, this is He Shuheng.
这位 这位是何叔衡
How do you do.
你好你好
And '28 Strokes Student' is...
这二十八画生是
He'll be right back.
他一会儿就回来
Eat first.
先吃饭吧
Ok.
好
I've found a treasure! I've found a treasure!
我淘到宝贝啦
28 Strokes Student is back.
二十八画生回来了
Mother Ge.
葛妈妈
You've worked hard.
您辛苦了
Runzhi,
润之啊
What are you talking about?
你这唱的哪一出啊
"Sent to the foothills"
纳于大麓
"Hidden in the famous mountains"
藏之名山
Ah, right.
对呀
From "The Book of Documents"
书经日
"Sent to the foothills"
纳于大麓
"Though he is late because of thunder and rain, he is not lost."
烈风雷雨弗迷
28 Strokes Student,
二十八画生
I believe,
我相信
the Heavens is about to confer a great responsibility.
天必降大任于斯人也
Runzhi, a new friend.
润之新朋友
"Whoever rescues the nation"
匡复属何人
"Is considered a kindred spirit."
君为知音者
New friend,
这位新朋友
what is your name?
请问尊姓大名啊
You are too kind.
尊字不敢当
My name is Li Lisan.
我叫李立三
I come from Liling, Hunan.
湖南陵人
I am '28 Strokes Student'
我是二十八画生
Mao Zedong.
毛泽东
Hello. How do you do.
你好 你好
Please sit.
请坐
Take a look at my treasure.
先看看我的宝贝
Sure.
好嘞
What treasure?
什么宝贝啊
Come, come, come.
来来来
Lend a hand.
帮帮忙 帮帮忙
Runzhi,
润之
To the side.
挪一下
Lost your manners?
失态了啊
You'll know it when you see it.
你看看就知道啦
Here.
来
Look.
看看
This is my treasure.
这就是我的宝贝
One for each.
一人一本啊
One book a person.
一人一本
Today,
今天
at our recruitment meeting,
我们这个征友会
let's discuss this,
别的不谈
and nothing else.
就谈这个
Come, take a look.
来看看
Look at this first,
你先看看这个
Look, look.
看看看看
This really is a treasure.
这真是宝贝
Everyone,
诸位
This is Mr. Chen Duxiu's "The Youth Magazine."
陈独秀先生主编的《青年杂志》
Mr. Yang Changji
杨昌济先生
has already recommended it to us many times.
曾多次给我们推荐过
He says it is the prescription to save the nation.
说是找到了救国的药方
Run Huan is right.
这润寰说得对
This is the remedy that will save lives.
这个啊就是救命的药
I've only
我刚才
briefly skimmed the founding statement.
只是简单地浏览了一下创刊词
Reading
看到这个
"A Call to the Youth"
《敬告青年》
I felt as if
我就已经觉得
I've been struck by a thunderbolt.
头上炸出了一道惊雷
Absolutely enlightening!
醍醐灌顶 醍醐灌顶
Runzhi,
润之啊
You've bought so many issues at once.
你一下子买了这么多杂志
How are you going to eat this month?
你这个月吃什么呀
'Tis enough to have this book.
吾有此书足矣
Runzhi,
润之啊
don't worry and read your book.
你就安心读你的书
If you do get hungry
要是真饿肚子了
come to Mother Ge
就到葛妈妈这儿来
and you'll definitely
保准啊
eat your fill.
让你吃个饱
Here. Great.
来 好
I'm actually hungry.
我还真饿了
You've reminded me.
你还真提醒我了
Mother Ge,
葛妈妈
remember to make it spicy.
记得辣子多来一点啊
The very spicy kind.
要辣得很的那种
Got it for you.
够你吃的
Thank you!
谢谢您啊
Everyone,
各位
I'm so energized.
我现在浑身都是劲儿
Haven't we always been talking
咱们不是一直在说
about creating a new people?
要再造新民吗
Well, what is the new youth?
那何为新青年呢
Mr. Chen Zhongfu
陈仲甫先生
right here
就在这里
talks about six criteria.
谈到了六条标准
Be independent, and not servile.
自主的而非奴隶的
Be progressive, and not conservative.
进步的而非保守的
Be aggressive, and not retiring.
进取的而非退隐的
Be cosmopolitan, and not isolationist.
世界的而非锁国的
Be utilitarian, and not formalistic.
实利的而非虚文的
Be scientific, and not fanciful.
科学的而非想象的
Wonderfully put!
说得太好了
The six criteria proposed by Mr. Zhongfu
仲甫先生提出的这六条啊
is exactly the direction to work towards
正是我辈今后
for my generation.
努力的方向
True.
对呀
These six criteria are good,
这六条标准虽好
but I don't think
但是我觉得啊
they are comprehensive enough.
还不够全面
What do you mean?
此话怎讲啊
I just feel
我觉得呀
there needs to be at least one more.
至少再加上一条
Be sturdy, and not frail.
健壮的而非体弱的
Tell me more.
愿闻其详
Everyone,
各位
our nation's scholars are more often
这我国士人啊
bookish and frail.
文弱者多
A military spirit has not been encouraged.
武风不振
Only when the young people boldly striving to save the country
敢于努力救国之新青年
are physically strong,
筋骨强
can their efforts be similarily vigorous.
方能气力雄
Then the moniker bestowed on us by foreigners
才能真的把外国人
"the sick man of Asia"
叫我们东亚病夫的帽子
can be actually thrown off completely.
彻底地踩在脚下
Well said. Makes sense.
说得好 有道理
I approve.
我赞同
I approve as well.
我也赞同 我也同意
Yes, I also agree.
对 我也同意
You're getting soaked!
淋湿了 淋湿了
Don't worry.
别着急 别着急
He's just like this.
他就这样
Civilize the mind,
文明其思想
make savage the body.
野蛮其体
With both strength of body and strength of convictions
心力体力合二为
There's nothing on earth that's impossible.
世上事未有不成
Everyone,
各位
This is
这才是
the new youth of China.
我们中国的新青年
I've thought about it.
我已经想好了
I am going to contribute to "Youth Magazine"
我要投稿《青年杂志》
and discuss in depth
好好地谈一谈
the physical education of Chinese people.
我们中国人自己的体育
Good, good.
好 好
Like many young students
和许多苦苦追求
who struggled to find the truest way to save the country,
救国真理的青年学子一样
Moa Zedong's eyes were opened by the magazine "New Youth."
毛泽东被《新青年》打开了眼界
He started to explore
他开始循着
the ideas of the early New Culture Movement.
初期新文化运动的思路探索
During this period,
这期间
he wrote these words in his diary:
他在日记里写下这样的话
In struggling with the sky, is there boundless joy.
与天奋斗 其乐无穷
In struggling with the earth, is there boundless joy.
与地奋斗 其乐无穷
In struggling with the people, is there boundless joy.
与人奋斗 其乐无穷
Students,
各位同学
I read
我看了这本
this newly published "Youth Magazine"
新出刊的《青年杂志》
and was immediately attracted by the
下被陈独秀先生写的创判词
inaugural address "A Call to Youth" by Mr.Chen Duxiu. [Zhou Enlai, styled Xiang Yu, Nankai School Student]
《敬告青年》所吸引住了
It was like a bright lamp
它就像一盏明灯
that illuminated my mind,
照亮了我的心智
It made me feel like
让我感到我以前的
everything I've thought and learned and done before
所思所学所行
was all for nought.
实在是一无所取
Therefore, I plan to switch
所以 我打算更换一下
my oral reading
我朗读的文章
with this issue of "Youth Magazine"
读一读这篇《敬告青年》
to share my delight with everyone.
同大家一同分享我心中的快活
Compariots desiring to leave the age of ignorance,
国人而欲脱蒙味时代
ashamed of their simple mindedness,
浅化之民世寿
and eager to catch up,
则急起直追
must pay equal attention to scientific knowledge and human rights.
当以科学与人权并重
Our scholars do not know science.
士不知科学
So they follow the Naturalists' School of auspicious signs and five elements.
故袭阴阳家符瑞五行之说
Confusing the world and cheating the people.
惑世证民
Our farmers do not know science.
农不知科学
So they have no methods for seed selection or insecticide.
故无择种去虫之术
Our industrialists do not know science.
工不知科学
So goods lie wasted on the ground,
故货弃于地
as we are dependent on foreign countries.
仰给于异国
Our merchants do not know science.
商不知科学
So they only care about short term profits,
故惟识图取近利
without any thought for planning for the future.
未来之胜算 无容心焉
Our physicians do not know science.
医不知科学
So they are not acquainted with human anatomy.
既不解人身之构造
The truth
宇宙间
in the universe is boundless.
之事理无穷
The fertile realms of science awaiting the trailblazer
科学领土内之膏腴待辟者
are immense!
正自广阔
Youth, take up the task!
青年勉乎哉
Strike your little gong.
擦啦啦小锡敲起来
"Youth Magazine" has been published.
《青年杂志》已出版
Chinese society has many difficulties.
中国社会多磨难
Mr. Chen Duxiu has shared two prescriptions with the public.
陈独秀两张药方来公开
Mr. Democracy and Mr. Science
德先生 赛先生
has already come to China.
已经跑到中国来
King of steel, Carnegie.
钢铁大王卡内基
That's Carnegie, not Shmarnegie.
卡内基啊 不是三黄鸡啊
Wonderful! Wonderful!
好 好
Turns out he was originally just a working boy.
他原来是一个打工的小男孩
Hello, excuse me.
你好 让一下
Take a look, take a peek.
看一看 瞧一瞧了
"Youth Magazine"
《青年杂志》
Mr. Democracy and Mr. Science are here.
德先生和赛先生来了
See how Carnegie fulfilled the American Dream.
看卡内基如何圆了美国梦
How he went from a worker to the king of steel!
从打工者到钢铁大王
Here, take a look.
来 您看一下
"Youth Magazine" Come, take a look. Newest edition.
最新一期的《青年杂志》
Take a look.
您看一下
Together?
起的是吧好一
Thank you, thank you.
谢谢您 谢谢您
"Youth Magazine"
《青年杂志》
He's from my hometown.
我的这位小乡党啊
His name is Hu Shi.
名字叫胡适
When he was nineteen years old
这孩子十九岁啊
he went to study abroad in the US,
到美国去留学去了
first at Cornell University to study agricultural science,
先在这个康奈尔大学学农学
then he switched his major to literature.
后来改读文学学院
He went to Columbia University this year
今年又去了哥伦比亚大学
to study with that well-known professor, John Dewey,
同那个著名的教授杜威
for a doctorate of philosophy.
攻读哲学博士学位
It can be said that this child
也可以说这孩子
is proficient in literature, history, and philosophy.
文史哲是样样精通
He saw an issue of our "Youth Magazine"
这不 看了咱们的《青年杂志》
and was very excited.
很激动
He's sent a letter
就写了这封信来
and wants to write an article regarding the revolution in literature.
他想写一篇关于文学革命的文章
So I would like to solicit your opinions.
所以我就征求一下你们意见
That's great!
太好了
This topic of literary revolution is great.
文学革命这个题目太好了
I really didn't expect
我真的没有想到
a student who has been overseas for years
个在国外留学多年的学生
to be capable of seeing the purpose of my magazine
能够对我陈独秀办杂志的心思
so incisively.
看得这么透彻
Genius!
奇才啊
A kindred spirit!
知音啊
Alright, Zhong Fu
仲甫 过了过了
A sworn friend!
伯牙子期啊
That's enough.
过了过了
Zhong Fu, a young man's letter
仲甫 一个后生的来信
can get you so excited?
你至于那么激动吗
Aren't you too ridiculous?
太夸张了吧你
Not by half!
半点都不夸张
Ideological guidance cannot be idle chit-chat,
思想启蒙不能空谈
but start from a concrete basis
要从具体做起
that focuses on the lives of the masses.
要着眼大生活
"Literary Revolution: A Tentative Proposal"
《文学革议刍议》
If this article is written properly,
这篇文章要是写好了
it will be a bombshell!
那就是一颗炸弹
Bai Sha, the younger generation will in time surpass us!
白沙 后生可畏啊
This Hu Shi
这个胡适
is too important for our "Youth Magazine."
对我们的《青年杂志》太重要了
Must grab him!
一定要抓住他
Oh Zhong Fu,
仲甫啊
in this time and age,
这个时代
it's not easy to find a genius
还有能入你陈独秀法眼的奇才
who can catch your eye.
这可真不容易啊
Though don't get too hung up on it.
不过你也别想得太好了
This guy is a doctoral student in the United States,
人家是美国的博士学生
and a disciple of Professor Dewey.
还是杜威教授的门徒
As if you can grab him just by saying so.
那是你说抓住就能抓住的
This guy lives in the United States.
人家身在美国
Whether he can even come back is an issue.
那能不能回来都是个问题
No, no. This I can guarantee.
不不 这个我敢打保票
He will definitely return to China after completing his studies.
他学成之后肯定回国
How can one be sure?
何以见得呀
This guy, Hu Shi,
这个胡适啊
is a filial son.
他是个孝子
Before he went abroad to study,
他在出国留学之前
his mother arranged a marriage for him.
他母亲呢就给他定了一门娃娃亲
His mother can't wait to get a grandson.
这个他母亲抱孙子心切呀
So she writes him letters every few days
就三天两头地给湖适写信
telling him to come back after he finishes his studies to get married.
说学成以后先回来完婚
He would not dare to disobey his mother.
他不敢违抗母命的
This person is really too wonderful.
这个人真是太好了
His thinking is wonderful.
想法太好了
What?
什么
Grab him!
抓住他
Grab him as soon as he comes back.
他一回来就抓住他
Junman!
君曼
Here, let me.
来 我来我来 我来
Why is your cough so bad?
怎么咳这么厉害啊
You took your medicine?
吃药了吗
I did. It's not effective.
吃了 不管用啊
It's not effective?
吃了不管用
You have to keep taking it.
那药得坚持吃
How can the medicine work if you don't keep taking it?
不坚持吃怎么管用啊
I've finished it.
我都吃光了
But there were no results.
就是没有什么效果嘛
You've finished it.
吃光了
Ok, alright.
行了行了行了
Don't work any more.
你别干活了
Go rest in the house.
去 进屋歇着去
Let me sit here for a bit.
你让我在这儿坐会儿
Get some air.
我透透气
Then wait. I will go buy medicine.
那你等着 我拿钱买药去
You don't need to go.
你不用去了
The drawer has long run out of money.
抽展里早没钱了
The money you gave me last month is all used up.
上个月你给我的钱都用光了
It's an old problem.
我这就是老病根了
It'll pass.
忍忍就过去了
Don't worry. I'm not dying.
没事 我死不了
Gao Junman!
高君曼
Don't work anymore!
别干活了
No one's dying if the firewood's not chopped.
那柴火你不雾他也死不了人
Go inside and rest.
屋里歇着去
Wait for me.
等着我
No one's dying if the firewood's not chopped.
柴火不劈死不了人
Can't cook if the firewood's not chopped!
那柴火不雾还锅都开不了呢
Zhong Fu,
仲甫
why are you here in such a heavy rain?
这么大的雨你怎么来了
Just dropping by.
我来看看
Pour your own tea if you want.
要喝茶自己倒啊
Those the accounts?
算账呢
So today,
我今天啊
I ran around to collect the money.
跑了一圈去收账
To date, our "Youth Magazine"
到今天呢 咱们的《青年杂志》
has sold 2000 copies in total,
一共销售了是两千本
breaking even.
收支平衡
The principal has basically been recouped.
本金基本上回笼了
That's great.
这太好了
That's a good thing, right?
这是个好事情
Mengzou,
孟邹
My uh...
我那个
This issue's payment for uh,
这一期的稿费呀
for my editorial.
编辑费呀
Is that included in the capital?
这个算不算本金里的
I'm calculating the big accounts.
我现在算的是大账
Haven't had a chance yet to take you into consideration.
还没来得及顾上你
Hold on, you have to take me into consideration as well.
你别呀你也顾得上我呀
If your capital has been recouped
你这本金都回笼了
then shouldn't the payment for my editorial
我那个稿费 编辑费
be given back to me?
是不也得回到我这儿来
Alright, then let me take you into consideration right now.
好 那我现在就顾及顾及你啊
Let me see,
我想想
Your manuscript fee, editorial fee
你的稿费 编辑费
added together
总共加起来
is 138 silver dollars.
是一百三十八块大洋
However, you've asked three times for an advance.
但是呢 你支借了三次钱
The first time, for 4 silver dollars.
一次是四块
The second time, also for 4 silver dollars.
这第二次也是四块
The third time, for 10 silver dollars.
第三次呢是十块
18 all together.
共十八块
138 minus 18
一百三十八减去十八
So you should get
你实得的呢
120 silver dollars, correct?
应该是一百二十块大洋 对吗
I'll give it to you right now.
我现在就给你啊
Fifty.
五十
One hundred.
一百
One twenty.
一百二
Take it.
你收好喽
I borrowed money three times.
我借了三次钱
Two $4 and one $10.
两个四块的一个十块的
Why don't I have any impression of this?
我怎么没印象啊
These matters, you don't need to think over it.
这些事啊你就不用考虑了
These are the matters I'll look after.
这是我管的事
As for you, great thinker
你呢大思想家
just unhesitatingly let out your brilliance.
就尽管地放光芒吧
Zhong Fu,
仲甫啊
you say, this Yuan Shikai,
你说这袁世凯啊
his determination to be the emperor
这铁了心了要当这个皇帝
makes the heavens angry and causes people to resent.
是天怒人怨
This authority, right now also has no time
这当局呢现在也没那个时间
to deal with the revolutionaries.
顾得上革命党人了
As soon as the current political situation starts to ease
这个时局一宽松
this business opportunity, it will come.
这商机它就来了
I want to seize onto the opportunity, go out and raise capital.
我想趁势而上出去招股
With your great persona, you will have a lot of acquaintances.
你这个大名人熟人多
Bring over more people with money to invest.
多拉几个有钱人来入股
This magazine of ours, maybe it will resume operations.
咱们这个杂志没准它就盘活了
Alright. No problem.
好没问题
You're responsible for finding people, I'll show up personally.
你负责找人我出面
As long as the magazine can be managed well,
只要能把杂志办好
whatever you have me do is fine.
你让我干什么都行
Uncle Wang.
汪伯伯
You've come back.
回来了
Dad.
爸
Why have you come back so early today?
今天怎么回来这么早啊
It's raining today, impossible to work.
今天下雨没法出工
Mengzou
孟邹
This... Yannian and Qiaonian doing editing here,
这个延年乔年在这儿做编务
isn't it that they should have pay too?
是不是也应该有工资啊
I gave it to them, Yannian didn't want it.
我给他们延年不要
Speaking about this pay,
说这个工资呢
it's made up for in my accommodation fees here.
就抵了在我这儿的住宿费了
I want to properly discuss with you,
我正想跟你说道说道
these two children's matters.
这俩孩子的事呢
In the daytime, they are working at the port.
这白天在搬运站打工
At night, they come over to my place to be editors.
晚上回来到我这儿当编务
And they still need to learn French.
还要学习法语
Wouldn't you say these two children are too tired
你说这俩孩子是不是太累了
That is to say, the two brothers living costs right now,
就是说现在他们哥俩生活费用
all depends on the salary from working at the port.
都是靠那个搬运站的那点工钱
That's right.
是啊
I have also heard, at the port they
我还听说他们在搬运站啊
extended the working time.
这打工的时间延长了
I quietly asked Qiaonian
我悄地问那个乔年
what's going on?
我说怎么回事啊
He said it's for getting the tuition to learn French.
他说呢是为了学习法语携学费
You say, what to do?
你说怎么办
This child, right now
这孩子你说现在
when his body is still growing.
他正长身体的时候
If he's like this, wouldn't his body break down?
这样的话那不把身体累了吗
You say, what to do with this?
你说怎么办这个
Those two, if they didn't want the editing pay,
他们俩的那个编务费不要了
you should give it me.
你应该给我呀
I am his father.
我是他老子
It should be me... Receiving it...
应该我我收着也
It should be normal too, right?
也正常吧对吧
What! This is...
什么呀你这是
That's another matter!
一码归一码啊
Didn't I already tell you?
我不是跟你说了吗
Yannian had the pay
延年把这工资
included it in the accommodation fees here.
就冲了在这儿的住宿费了
You still say your son and you are very similar,
你还说你儿子跟你很像
not even a little similar.
点都不像
He, give him money and he doesn't want it.
他呢给钱不要
You here, keep going on and on with me.
你这儿还跟我没完没了了你
This is 50 silver dollars.
这是五十块大洋
100 silver dollars.
百块大洋
This is 20.
这二十
Dad, what are you giving me so much..
爸你给我这么多干
Listen to me.
你听我说
This money, I give it to you two brothers to pay tuition.
这钱啊是我给你们哥俩交学费的
Understand?
明白吗
Quickly go.
赶紧走
Zhong Fu.
仲甫
You already gave it.
你都给了
Mengzou.
孟邹
You say, just now
你说刚才
said something like I borrowed money three times.
说什么我借了三次钱
$4 twice, $10 once.
两次四块一次十块
When was that?
那什么时候事啊
How come I don't have any impression.
我怎么一点没印象
Let me look at the account.
你给我看看账
Don't talk about these things with me anymore.
别跟我说这些了啊
I'll draw some money for you again,
我再支给你点
not for drawing some money for myself.
不是再支给我点
I'll look at the account. How come I didn't...
我看看账我怎么就没
Stop there!
站住
Chen Yannian!
陈延年
This money is to give you two brothers to pay tuition.
这个钱是给你们哥俩交学费的
Am I wrong?
我有错吗
Don't need it.
不需要
Today, you say it to me clearly.
你今天跟我说清楚
What is it about me that you are so against?
你最反对我的是什么
You are too greedy.
你这个人太贪心
You want both a family and to love your country.
既想要家 又想爱国
Is there a contradiction between these two?
这两者有矛盾吗
There is a contradiction.
有矛盾
If you want to love your country, then you must give up the family.
若要爱国则必舍家
Otherwise, you will only give the family
否则你只会给家庭
an even greater harm.
造成更大的伤害
You really feel your assertion has value?
你真的觉得你坚持的有价值吗
At least, currently, yes.
至少日前是
Good! Then you keep insisting!
好那你坚持吧
Go! Go!
走走
Yannian. Yannian!
延年啊延年
Zhong Fu!
仲甫
Being older, wants to chat
老想谈
but it collapses with a single conversation.
一谈就崩
Shou Chang
守常
Did you see the announcement at the school's entrance?
你看到学校门口的告示了吗
The school is known for its long-standing lack of learning.
学校以长期欠习为名
You have been expelled!
把你给除名了
I saw it. This was within my expectations.
看见了意料中的事
I've been struggling for months.
本来纠结了好几个月
It's done now. I've got a result.
现在好了有结果了
I can completely focus on taking care of the revolution now.
我可以心无旁地搞革命了
Brother Shouchang
守常兄
It's completely me who harmed you
都是我把你给害了
At that time, I really shouldn't have insisted on pulling you
当初我真不应该非要拉你
to be the editor-in-chief of "Minyi" magazine.
来当这个《民鑫》杂志的主编
You were originally at the Foreign Students Assocation in Japan
你本来在留日学生总会
being the head editor in the literature and history committee
文史委员会当编辑主任
were already very busy.
已经都非常忙了呀
It doesn't have to do with you.
不关你的事啊
It's I who likes to edit magazines.
是我自己喜欢编杂志
Right now, Yuan Shikai acts an emperor.
现在袁世凯当了皇帝
The country is already successfully thrown into a complete mess.
国内已经乱成一锅粥了
I absolutely can not calm down my heart to read books.
我根本静不下心来读书
What plans do you have?
你有什么打算
First, wholeheartedly
先全心全意地
edit the first issue of "Minyi" magazine
把《民鑫》杂志创刊号编好
have it become the rallying cry that denounces Yuan Shikai.
让它成为海外讨袁的号角
Then, I'll return to the country. Head to the battlefield.
然后我就回国上战场
Listening to you like this, I also can't sit still.
听你这么一说我也坐不住了
Anyway, I am also graduating soon
反正我也快毕业了
When the time comes, I'll return with you.
到时候我跟你一块回国
but returning to the main topic,
不过话又说回来
if we're really going to the firing line to fire guns and battle.
真上火线打枪打仗
I don't know if I can do it.
我不知道我能不能行
Who says you have to fight Yuan with real weapons?
谁说讨袁非得真刀真枪啊
Chen Duxiu's ideological enlightenment of the youth
人家陈独秀搞思想启蒙
was the same as the Yuan struggle.
那是一样讨袁
Moreover, he did it from the roots.
而且是从根上讨
It's not bad compared to the results of a firearm.
不比枪炮的效果差
Shouchang, I heard that his magazine
守常听说他的杂志
ran into big trouble.
遇到了大麻烦
Already stopped publishing.
已经停刊了
I know.
我知道
Small trouble. It's almost resolved.
小麻烦差不多快解决了
Just change the publication name, and it's fine.
换一个刊名就行了
Right now, I am in the middle of
我现在正在
writing an article for the relaunch issue.
为他的复刊号写文章呢
You are? Can I take a look?
是吗我看看
What a great title for "Youth".
《青春》好题目啊
This long?
这么长
I'll read it to you. You try to feel it.
我给你念念你感觉感觉
Yes, yes.
好啊好啊
When the Earth turns white,
地球即成白首
we are still in our youth.
吾人尚在青春
We use our youth,
以吾人之青春
To softly change earth's whiteness.
柔化地球之白首
Although old, yet not old
虽老犹未老也
is the Earth's one day of existence.
是则地球一日存在
That is, our youth exists for one day.
即吾人之青春一日存在
Our youth exists for one day.
吾人之青春一日存在
That is, the youth of the earth exists for one day.
即地球之青春一日存在
In 1916,
一九一六年
Li Dazhao wrote his famous article
李大钊在日本写下了著名的
"Youth", in Japan.
《青春》一文
The article used an uplifting revolutionary spirit
文章以昂扬的革命精神
and a scientific approach to humanism
和科学的人生态度
expressing an clear materialistic ideology,
表达了明显的唯物主义思想
proposing the ideal of rejuvenating China's youth.
提出了再造青春中华的理想主张
Calling young people
号召青年
to break through the snares of past history,
冲决过去历史之网罗
destroy stereotypical doctrines,
破坏陈腐学说之图图
use the spirit of youth to continuously transform oneself,
以青春的精神不断改造自我
use the vitality of youth, the ideals of youth
以青春的朝气青春的理想
to wake up the old China from the century of dormancy,
唤醒百年沉睡的旧中国
and establish a youthful China.
建立青春之中华
Hurry, hurry, hurry. It's freezing.
快快快冻坏了吧
[First-rate Xiang hotel, Shanghai]
[上海一品香旅社]
[Wu Zhihui a.k.a. Jing Heng]
[吴椎晖 又名 敬恒]
Hurry, come warm up in the fire.
快来烤烤火
Quickly sit, quickly sit. Warm up.
快坐快坐烤烤火
Knowing I came back,
知道我回来了
you guys even came to see me. Good!
你们还来看看我好
By contrast, your guys' father
反观你们的父亲
don't know if he doesn't welcome me back.
也不知道他是不欢迎我回国呢
Or he is scared that I will snatch his profits,
还是怕我抢了他的彩头
so he's pulling his strong card with me
跟我要大牌
It's already been so long, and he doesn't come to see me,
你说都这么了他也不来看看我
he is really worse than a child.
真是连孩子都不如啊
What is Chen Duxiu busy with?
陈独秀忙什么呢
"Youth Magazine" became renowned with other people.
《青年杂志》跟人家重名了
It was sued by others for breach of reputation
让人家告了侵犯名誉权
and so stopped publishing.
给停刊了
He's been busy with the lawsuit.
他就一直忙着打官司呢
Who is so insensitive?
谁这么没有眼力见儿
Dare to dispute with the enlightened great master Chen Duxiu?
敢跟启蒙大师陈独秀打官司
Isn't this finding trouble by yourself?
这不是自取其吗
Okay, okay. Let's not talk about him now.
好了好了我们不说他了
How are you guys doing?
你们怎么样
Living, isn't it very tough?
生活得是不是很辛苦啊
We aren't afraid of hardship!
我们不怕辛苦
We two have been working while studying.
我俩一直在勤工俭学
Living life to the fullest!
过得很充实
Good. Good.
好好啊
I didn't misjudge you guys.
我没看错你们
I'll tell you guys.
我跟你们说啊
I returned this time,
我这趟回国
first is to assist in overthrowing the Lord Protector Yuan,
是襄助倒袁护国
second is to launch a campaign for a work-study program for those who will stay in France.
二是启动留法勤工俭学运动
Didn't you guys want to go to France?
你们不是要去法国吗
Let me test you guys.
我来考考你们
Nowadays, what is the most popular theory in the West?
当今西方最流行的理论是什么
Charles Darwin's Theory of Evolution!
达尔文的进化论
That's not simple,
不简单哪
who told you this?
谁告诉你的
I overheard it too
我也是偷听到的
Hunan and Anhui comrades held a meeting.
湘皖同志开会
Chen Duxiu gave everyone
陈独秀给大家
an explanation on the Theory of Evolution all morning
讲了一上午的进化论
saying that natural selection is an unchanging truth
说物竞天择是万古不变的真理
and is the motivation for human progress
也是人类进步的动力
In this, Chen Duxiu is ignorant and narrow-minded.
陈独秀这是坐井观天
He only knows the first thing and not the second.
他是只知其一不知其二
Actually, the popular theory nowadays
其实当今最流行的理论
is not Darwin's Theory of Evolution,
不是达尔文的进化论
rather it's Kropotkin's Theory of Mutual Assistance.
而是克鲁泡特金的互助论
Come.
来
This is some material from France that I specially
这是我特意从法国
brought back for you guys.
给你们带回来的一些资料
You guys carefully take a look at it.
你们好好看看
I guarantee
我保证
as you guys understand it more and more,
随着你们对它越来越了解
you will for sure deeply fall in love with it.
你们一定会深深爱上它的
Take a look, take a look.
看看看看
March 1916
一九一六年三月
amidst the outcry at home and abroad
在海内外一片声讨声中
Yuan Shikai was forced to cancel his autocratic monarchy.
袁世凯被迫取消帝制
A shameful performance full of a farce to restore an autocratic monarchy
一场丑态百出的复壁帝制的闹剧
came to a premature end.
天折
Since the Xinhai Revolution,
自辛亥革命以来
due to the fact that in China
由于在中国
the idea to establish a bourgeois republic
建立资产阶级共和国的主张
was out of step with the Chinese situation,
脱离中国国情
the old democratic revolution
领导旧民主主义革命的
lead by China's bourgeoisie
中国资产阶级
cannot obtain the extensive support of the working class.
得不到劳动人民的广泛支持
Hitting a wall in all directions. Suffering defeat in every battle.
四处碰壁履战败
A difficult situation.
处境限难
Yuan Shikai, who represents the feudal power of China
代表中国封建势力的袁世凯
was regarded as taking away the achievements of the Xinhai Revolution, and met with contempt after his death.
算夺辛亥革命成果被弃而死后
Revolutionists who were forced into exile overseas returned to the country one after another
流亡海外的革命者纷纷回国
Li Dazhao
李大钊
invited to visit Beijing
应邀赴北京
took the post of editor-in-chief of "Morning Bell" newspaper.
担任《晨钟报》主编
At this time, after the baptism of the anti-Yuan movement
此时经过倒袁运动的洗礼
initially accepting
初步接受
the historical materialism point of view, Li Dazhao
历史唯物主义观点的李大
already became a revolutionary full of new ideas.
充满新思想的革命家已经成为了
Brother. Where is your home?
兄弟家在哪儿住啊
Outside Yongdingmen. The pariah.
永定门外贱民一个
Why do you say this?
这话怎么说
Those who pull carts, wield skill in trade
拉车的要把式的
have shaved heads, are pig butchers, coffin carriers,
剃头的杀猪的
all live over there.
都住咱们那边
Then how is getting by in life right now for you guys?
那你们现在生活过得怎么样啊
Impossible to get by. Everyone's suffering until they can't take it anymore.
没法过呀都苦到顶了
According to the older generations' saying,
按老辈的话说
we have never gone through such sullen days.
就没过过这么整屈的日子